Let's do one more example.
One last video for this week.
An example of
this connection between mathematical
and graphical representation
of Petri nets.
I had just briefly outlined on the slide
the way that we have a Petri net
in graphical representation and we
read the mathematical representation from that.
Of course, you have to be able
to do that the other way around.
So here is an old exercise where
the mathematical representation of a Petri net was
given, and the question was asked
for the corresponding graphically represented Petri net.
And I would now simply develop this with
you briefly here, i.e. demonstrate it to you.
So, what do we have?
We have given information about the
number and ultimately identity
of places and transitions.
So, what we see here is:
There are three places s1, s2, s3
and four transitions t1, t2, t3, t4.
So we can draw those in already.
Maybe I have to make it
a little bit bigger, as a circle.
So, this one looks good.
So I have here a place s1,
a place s2 and a place s3.
Okay, so I've already used
up this information, so to speak.
Then there should be four
transitions t1, t2, t3, t4.
I would have to
arrange them somewhere first.
So let's say for example, I
have here t1, t2, t3 and t4.
Then I would have used
up that information as well.
But the relevant information is,
of course, primarily what is said here.
Or first, I might want to
use the information about the start marking.
It says the start marking for s1 is 2
and for s2 as well as for s3 is 0.
This means that I must have two tokens on
the first position and
nothing on the other two.
I help myself in such a way that
I now have the two tokens on s1.
Then I have used
the information down here about
the start marking
for the individual places.
And then I can deal with the arrows.
What it says here.
You can see here:
There are three places, four transitions.
There could well be more
entries than are written here.
Because we have to specify pre- and
post-weights for each transition for each place.
Here, 10 values are explicitly given.
And for all others, it says
here below, the value is 0.
All other weights are 0.
That is, we won't find
them in the graphical representation.
We just have to draw in
all the entries from here as arrows.
And there we just
start with the first one.
So what does this entry want to tell us?
It says:
For t1, the pre-weight
of s1 is exactly 1.
That means there must
be such an arrow here.
Okay, that's what that
first line there says.
What does the second line say?
The second line says:
For t2, there must be an input
arrow from s2 with the value 1.
And "with the value 1" simply means that there is
an arrow here, but there is no weight on it.
So from s2 to t2 there must be an arrow.
Let that be this one.
Okay, to t2 there must
also be an arrow from s3.
Let that be this one.
To t3, there must be an
arrow from s3, with weight 2.
So from s3 to t3, because that's
the pre-weight for t3 with respect to s3.
So from s3 to t3 an arrow, with weight 2.
That's why we add a two to the arrow.
And so it goes on.
So from s2 to t4 a simple arrow.
Now come the post-weights.
So from t1 to s3 a simple arrow.
We can draw it around here, for example.
From t2 to s1 with weight 2.
From t3 to s1 a simple arrow.
From t3 to s2 a simple arrow.
And finally from t4 to s3.
And so, unless I somehow got it
wrong or forgot something, what we see
here now would be the
Petri net in graphical representation, which
corresponds to the
given mathematical representation.
You could maybe make that prettier.
You might have been able
to layout that even differently.
The nodes could have been
arranged differently in this graphical representation.
But that wouldn't make any difference.
Yes, if I were to somehow
move individual nodes somewhere else here
and drag the connection along, it
would still be the same Petri net.
That would just be a different graphical
representation for the same Petri net, and it
would be according to the
mathematical representation written down here before.
Okay, and you should be
able to do that both ways.